The  Lottery
By Shirley Jackson
The morning of June 27th was clear and sunny, with the fresh warmth of a full- summer day; the 
flowers were blossoming profusely and the grass was richly green. The people of the village began 
to gather in the square, between the post office and the bank, around ten o'clock; in some towns 
there were so many people that the lottery took two days and had to be started on June 2nd but in 
this village, where there were only about three hundred people, the whole lottery took less than 
two hours, so it could begin at ten o'clock in the morning and still be through in time to allow 
the villagers to get home for noon dinner.
The children assembled first, of course. School was recently over for the summer, and the feeling 
of liberty sat uneasily on most of them; they tended to gather together quietly for a while before 
they broke into boisterous play. and their talk was still of the classroom and the teacher, of 
books and reprimands.
Bobby Martin had already stuffed his pockets full of stones, and the other boys soon followed his 
example, selecting the smoothest and roundest stones; Bobby and Harry Jones and Dickie Delacroix-- 
the villagers pronounced this name "Dellacroy"--eventually made a great pile of stones in one 
corner of the square and guarded it against the raids of the other boys. The girls stood aside, 
talking among themselves, looking over their shoulders at rolled in the dust or clung to the hands 
of their older brothers or sisters.
Soon the men began to gather, surveying their own children, speaking of planting and rain, tractors 
and taxes. They stood together, away from the pile of stones in the corner, and their jokes were 
quiet and they smiled rather than laughed. The women, wearing faded house dresses and sweaters, 
came shortly after their menfolk. They greeted one another and exchanged bits of gossip as they 
went to join their husbands. Soon the
women, standing by their husbands, began to call to their children, and the children came 
reluctantly, having to be called four or five times. Bobby Martin ducked under his mother's 
grasping hand and ran, laughing, back to the pile of stones. His father spoke up sharply, and Bobby 
came quickly and took his place between his father and his oldest brother.
The lottery was conducted--as were the square dances, the teen club, the Halloween program--by Mr. 
Summers who had time and energy to devote to civic activities. He was a round-faced, jovial man and 
he ran the coal business, and people were sorry for him because he had no children and his wife was 
a scold. When he arrived in the square, carrying the black wooden box, there was a murmur of 
conversation among the villagers, and he waved and called, "Little late today, folks." The 
postmaster, Mr. Graves, followed him, carrying a three- legged stool, and the stool was put in the 
center of the square and Mr.
Summers set the black box down on it. The villagers kept their distance, leaving a space between 
themselves and the stool. and when Mr. Summers said, "Some of you fellows want to give me a hand?" 
there was a hesitation before two men, Mr. Martin and his oldest son, Baxter, came forward to hold 
the box steady on the stool while Mr. Summers stirred up the papers inside it.
The original paraphernalia for the lottery had been lost long ago, and the black box now resting on 
the stool had been put into use even before Old Man Warner, the oldest man in town, was born. Mr. 
Summers spoke frequently to the villagers about making a new box, but no one liked to upset even as 
much tradition as was represented by the black box. There was a story that the present box had been 
made with some pieces of the box that had preceded it, the one that had been constructed when the 
first people settled down to make a village here. Every year, after the lottery, Mr. Summers began 
talking again about a new box, but every year the subject was allowed to fade off without 
anything's being done. The black box grew shabbier each

- 1 -

year: by now it was no longer completely black but splintered badly along one side to show the 
original wood color, and in some places faded or stained.
Mr. Martin and his oldest son, Baxter, held the black box securely on the stool until Mr. Summers 
had stirred the papers thoroughly with his hand. Because so much of the ritual had been forgotten 
or discarded, Mr. Summers had been successful in having slips of paper substituted for the chips of 
wood that had been used for generations. Chips of wood, Mr. Summers had argued. had been all very 
well when the village was tiny, but now that the population was more than three hundred and likely 
to keep on growing, it was necessary to use something that would fit more easily into he black box. 
The night before the lottery, Mr. Summers and Mr.
Graves made up the slips of paper and put them in the box, and it was then taken to the safe of Mr. 
Summers' coal company and locked up until Mr. Summers was ready to take it to the square next 
morning. The rest of the year, the box was put way, sometimes one place, sometimes another; it had 
spent one year in Mr. Graves's barn and another year underfoot in the post office, and sometimes it 
was set on a shelf in the Martin grocery and left there.
There was a great deal of fussing to be done before Mr. Summers declared the lottery open. There 
were the lists to make up--of heads of families, heads of households in each family, members of 
each household in each family. There was the proper swearing-in of Mr. Summers by the postmaster, 
as the official of the lottery; at one time, some people remembered, there had been a recital of 
some sort, performed by the official of the lottery, a perfunctory. tuneless chant that had been 
rattled off duly each year; some people believed that the official of the lottery used to stand 
just so when he said or sang it, others believed that he was supposed to walk among the people, but 
years and years ago this p3rt of the ritual had been allowed to lapse. There had been, also, a 
ritual salute, which the official of the lottery had had to use in
addressing each person who came up to draw from the box, but this also had changed with time, until 
now it was felt necessary only for the official to speak to each person approaching. Mr. Summers 
was very good at all this; in his clean white shirt and blue jeans, with one hand resting 
carelessly on the black box. he seemed very proper and important as he talked interminably to Mr. 
Graves and the Martins.
Just as Mr. Summers finally left off talking and turned to the assembled villagers, Mrs. Hutchinson 
came hurriedly along the path to the square, her sweater thrown over her shoulders, and slid into 
place in the back of the crowd. "Clean forgot what day it was," she said to Mrs. Delacroix, who 
stood next to her, and they both laughed softly. "Thought my old man was out back stacking wood," 
Mrs. Hutchinson went on," and then I looked out the window and the kids was gone, and then I 
remembered it was the twenty-seventh and came a-running." She dried her hands on her apron, and 
Mrs. Delacroix said, "You're in time, though. They're still talking away up there."
Mrs. Hutchinson craned her neck to see through the crowd and found her husband and children 
standing near the front. She tapped Mrs. Delacroix on the arm as a farewell and began to make her 
way through the crowd. The people separated good- humoredly to let her through: two or three people 
said. in voices just loud enough to be heard across the crowd, "Here comes your, Missus, 
Hutchinson," and "Bill, she made it after all." Mrs. Hutchinson reached her husband, and Mr. 
Summers, who had been waiting, said cheerfully. "Thought we were going to have to get on without 
you, Tessie." Mrs. Hutchinson said, grinning, "Wouldn't have me leave m'dishes in the sink, now, 
would you, Joe?," and soft laughter ran through the crowd as the people stirred back into position 
after Mrs. Hutchinson's arrival.
"Well, now," Mr. Summers said soberly, "guess we better get started, get this over with, so's we 
can go back to work. Anybody ain't here?"

- 2 -

"Dunbar." several people said. "Dunbar.
Dunbar."
Mr. Summers consulted his list. "Clyde Dunbar." he said. "That's right. He's broke his leg, hasn't 
he? Who's drawing for him?"
"Me. I guess," a woman said. and Mr. Summers turned to look at her. "Wife draws for her husband." 
Mr. Summers said. "Don't you have a grown boy to do it for you, Janey?" Although Mr. Summers and 
everyone else in the village knew the answer perfectly well, it was the business of the official of 
the lottery to ask such questions formally. Mr.
Summers waited with an expression of polite interest while Mrs. Dunbar answered.
"Horace's not but sixteen vet." Mrs.
Dunbar said regretfully. "Guess I gotta fill in for the old man this year."
"Right." Sr. Summers said. He made a note on the list he was holding. Then he asked, "Watson boy 
drawing this year?"
A tall boy in the crowd raised his hand. "Here," he said. "I’m drawing for my mother and me." He 
blinked his eyes nervously and ducked his head as several voices in the crowd said things like 
"Good fellow, luck" and "Glad to see your mother's got a man to do it."
"Well," Mr. Summers said, "guess that's everyone. Old Man Warner make it?"
"Here," a voice said. and Mr. Summers nodded.
A sudden hush fell on the crowd as Mr. Summers cleared his throat and looked at the list. "All 
ready?" he called. "Now, I'll read the names--heads of families first--and the men come up and take 
a paper out of the box.
Keep the paper folded in your hand without looking at it until everyone has had a turn. Everything 
clear?"
The people had done it so many times that they only half listened to the directions: most of them 
were quiet, wetting their lips, not looking around. Then Mr. Summers raised one hand high and said, 
"Adams." A man disengaged himself from the crowd and came forward. "Hi. Steve." Mr. Summers said, 
and Mr. Adams said, "Hi. Joe." They grinned at one another humorlessly and nervously. Then Mr. 
Adams reached into the black box and
took out a folded paper. He held it firmly by one corner as he turned and went hastily back to his 
place in the crowd where he stood a little apart from his family, not looking down at his hand.
"Allen." Mr. Summers said. "Anderson  Bentham."
"Seems like there's no time at all between lotteries any more." Mrs. Delacroix said to Mrs. Graves 
in the back row.
"Seems like we got through with the last one only last week."
"Time sure goes fast,” Mrs. Graves said. "Clark  Delacroix"
"There goes my old man." Mrs.
Delacroix said. She held her breath while her husband went forward.
"Dunbar," Mr. Summers said, and Mrs. Dunbar went steadily to the box while one of the women said, 
"Go on, Janey," and another said, "There she goes."
"We're next." Mrs. Graves said. She watched while Mr. Graves came around from the side of the box, 
greeted Mr. Summers gravely and selected a slip of paper from the box. By now, all through the 
crowd there were men holding the small folded papers in their large hand, turning them over and 
over nervously. Mrs. Dunbar and her two sons stood together, Mrs. Dunbar holding the slip of paper.
"Harburt  Hutchinson."
"Get up there, Bill," Mrs. Hutchinson said. and the people near her laughed.
"Jones."
"They do say," Mr. Adams said to Old Man Warner, who stood next to him, "that over in the north 
village they're talking of giving up the lottery."
Old Man Warner snorted. "Pack of crazy fools," he said. "Listening to the young folks, nothing's 
good enough for them. Next thing you know, they'll be wanting to go back to living in caves, nobody 
work any more, live hat way for a while. Used to be a saying about 'Lottery in June, corn be heavy 
soon.' First thing you know, we'd all be eating stewed chickweed and acorns. There's always been a 
lottery," he added petulantly. "Bad enough to

- 3 -

see young Joe Summers up there joking with everybody."
"Some places have already quit lotteries." Mrs. Adams said.
"Nothing but trouble in that," Old Man Warner said stoutly. "Pack of young fools."
"Martin." And Bobby Martin watched his father go forward. "Overdyke  Percy."
"I wish they'd hurry," Mrs. Dunbar said to her older son. "I wish they'd hurry."
"They're almost through," her son said. "You get ready to run tell Dad," Mrs.
Dunbar said.
Mr. Summers called his own name and then stepped forward precisely and selected a slip from the 
box. Then he called, "Warner."
"Seventy-seventh year I been in the lottery," Old Man Warner said as he went through the crowd. 
"Seventy-seventh time."
"Watson" The tall boy came awkwardly through the crowd. Someone said, "Don't be nervous, Jack," and 
Mr. Summers said, "Take your time, son."
"Zanini."
After that, there was a long pause, a breathless pause, until Mr. Summers. holding his slip of 
paper in the air, said, "All right, fellows." For a minute, no one moved, and then all the slips of 
paper were opened.
Suddenly, all the women began to speak at once, saving. "Who is it?," "Who's got it?," "Is it the 
Dunbars?," "Is it the Watsons?" Then the voices began to say, "It's Hutchinson. It's Bill," "Bill 
Hutchinson's got it."
"Go tell your father," Mrs. Dunbar said to her older son.
People began to look around to see the Hutchinsons. Bill Hutchinson was standing quiet, staring 
down at the paper in his hand. Suddenly, Tessie Hutchinson shouted to Mr. Summers. "You didn't give 
him time enough to take any paper he wanted. I saw you. It wasn't fair!"
"Be a good sport, Tessie," Mrs.
Delacroix called, and Mrs. Graves said, "All of us took the same chance."
"Shut up, Tessie," Bill Hutchinson said. "Well, everyone," Mr. Summers said,
"that was done pretty fast, and now we've got
to be hurrying a little more to get done in time." He consulted his next list. "Bill," he said, 
"you draw for the Hutchinson family. You got any other households in the Hutchinsons?"
"There's Don and Eva," Mrs.
Hutchinson yelled. "Make them take their chance!"
"Daughters draw with their husbands' families, Tessie," Mr. Summers said gently. "You know that as 
well as anyone else."
"It wasn't fair," Tessie said.
"I guess not, Joe." Bill Hutchinson said regretfully. "My daughter draws with her husband's family; 
that's only fair. And I've got no other family except the kids."
"Then, as far as drawing for families is concerned, it's you," Mr. Summers said in explanation, 
"and as far as drawing for households is concerned, that's you, too.
Right?"
"Right," Bill Hutchinson said.
"How many kids, Bill?" Mr. Summers asked formally.
"Three," Bill Hutchinson said. "There's Bill, Jr., and Nancy, and little
Dave. And Tessie and me."
"All right, then," Mr. Summers said. "Harry, you got their tickets back?"
Mr. Graves nodded and held up the slips of paper. "Put them in the box, then," Mr. Summers 
directed. "Take Bill's and put it in."
"I think we ought to start over," Mrs. Hutchinson said, as quietly as she could. "I tell you it 
wasn't fair. You didn't give him time enough to choose. Everybody saw that."
Mr. Graves had selected the five slips and put them in the box. and he dropped all the papers but 
those onto the ground, where the breeze caught them and lifted them off.
"Listen, everybody," Mrs. Hutchinson was saying to the people around her.
"Ready, Bill?" Mr. Summers asked. and Bill Hutchinson, with one quick glance around at his wife and 
children nodded.
"Remember," Mr. Summers said. "take the slips and keep them folded until each person has taken one. 
Harry, you help little

- 4 -

Dave." Mr. Graves took the hand of the little boy, who came willingly with him up to the box. "Take 
a paper out of the box, Davy." Mr. Summers said. Davy put his hand into the box and laughed. "Take 
just one paper." Mr.
Summers said. "Harry, you hold it for him." Mr. Graves took the child's hand and removed the folded 
paper from the tight fist and held it while little Dave stood next to him and looked up at him 
wonderingly.
"Nancy next," Mr. Summers said. Nancy was twelve, and her school friends breathed heavily as she 
went forward switching her skirt, and took a slip daintily from the box. "Bill, Jr.," Mr. Summers 
said, and Billy, his face red and his feet overlarge, near knocked the box over as he got a paper 
out. "Tessie," Mr. Summers said. She hesitated for a minute, looking around defiantly and then set 
her lips and went up to the box. She snatched a paper out and held it behind her.
"Bill," Mr. Summers said, and Bill Hutchinson reached into the box and felt around, bringing his 
hand out at last with the slip of paper in it.
The crowd was quiet. A girl whispered, "I hope it's not Nancy," and the sound of the whisper 
reached the edges of the crowd.
"It's not the way it used to be." Old Man Warner said clearly. "People ain't the way they used to 
be."
"All right," Mr. Summers said. "Open the papers. Harry, you open little Dave's."
Mr. Graves opened the slip of paper and there was a general sigh through the crowd as he held it up 
and everyone could see that it was blank. Nancy and Bill, Jr. opened theirs at the same time and 
both beamed and laughed, turning around to the crowd and holding their slips of paper above their 
heads.
"Tessie," Mr. Summers said. There was a pause, and then Mr. Summers looked at Bill Hutchinson, and 
Bill unfolded his paper and showed it. It was blank.
"It's Tessie," Mr. Summers said, and his voice was hushed. "Show us her paper, Bill."
Bill Hutchinson went over to his wife and forced the slip of paper out of her hand. It had a black 
spot on it, the black spot Mr.
Summers had made the night before with the heavy pencil in the coal company office. Bill Hutchinson 
held it up, and there was a stir in the crowd.
"All right, folks." Mr. Summers said. "Let's finish quickly."
Although the villagers had forgotten the ritual and lost the original black box, they still 
remembered to use stones. The pile of stones the boys had made earlier was ready; there were stones 
on the ground with the blowing scraps of paper that had come out of the box Delacroix selected a 
stone so large she had to pick it up with both hands and turned to Mrs. Dunbar. "Come on," she 
said. "Hurry up."
Mr. Dunbar had small stones in both hands, and she said, gasping for breath. "I can't run at all. 
You'll have to go ahead and I'll catch up with you."
The children had stones already. And someone gave little Davy Hutchinson few pebbles.
Tessie Hutchinson was in the center of a cleared space by now and she held her hands out 
desperately as the villagers moved in on her. "It isn't fair," she said. A stone hit her on the 
side of the head. Old Man Warner was saying, "Come on, come on, everyone." Steve Adams was in the 
front of the crowd of villagers, with Mrs. Graves beside him.
"It isn't fair, it isn't right," Mrs.
Hutchinson screamed, and then they were upon her.

- 5 -
